the science elan podcast I'm your host
Michael Shermer as you all know we do
this once a week on the Tuesdays that
books are released this week's book and
author is my longtime friend Christoph
Kok his new book is the feeling of life
itself
why consciousness is widespread but
can't be computed so you can see where
that's going
I've known Christoph since the early 90s
so probably almost a quarter century now
he's one of the most interesting people
have ever met super delightful guy very
smart very witty and has a real lust for
life and he's now left Caltech and has
been at the Allen Brain Institute for I
don't know must be at least a decade now
and so we talked a little bit about that
the research and work that they do there
what are they doing when they're trying
to find the neural correlates of
consciousness we get into the hard
problem of consciousness and what that
means the integrated information theory
of consciousness versus the global work
space theory of consciousness and we
talked about comas and and vegetative
States and you know is there anybody
there how do we know they need to find
these things the nature of the self and
identity if you have a split brain
there's really two Minds so if you have
two Minds is that two persons two selves
you know what does that all mean so we
explore some of that and and pretty much
cover most of the the major
philosophical issues related to the
mind-body problem how consciousness
arrives from a physical system why he
thinks that no computer will ever be
conscious the what they're designed to
do and the underlying architecture the
structure of it of computers that as
currently configured will never ever be
conscious and he makes pretty good
argument I think not that it can't be
done it's just that it's not going to be
done the way we're doing it now I think
he's probably right in the sense that
you know it's a much harder problem than
anybody ever realized when we're talking
about creating conscious computers back
in the 90s and still hasn't happened I
think it's just way more difficult than
anybody realized and anyway it's a great
book it's really you know short straight
to the point he's a clear rider clear
thinker and again he really it's in the
title itself what is consciousness is
the feeling of life itself or as he says
even more succinctly it's its experience
consciousness is experience so
consciousness has lived reality it is
the feeling of life itself it is the
only bit of eternity to which I am
entitled without experience I would be a
zombie a nothing to myself anyway great
book if you appreciate the podcast as
usual we appreciate your support either
through patreon every month or at
skeptic comm / donate thank you I give
you Christophe
Christophe is that Francis Crick
behind you there yes it's a painting he
gave me it's a it's a photocopy of him
in its wicked share a half he gave that
to me half a year before he passed away
and it says for christophe francis
keeping an eye on you so you you have
them there in your office watching over
you at all times okay looking over my
shoulder at all times
yes and that also looks like the other
is that the cover of The Beatles Sgt
pepper's conferences
oh I see very good right fine yeah to
include David Thomas myself and two
other you know couple yeah yeah no
that's really funny yeah very good so I
am speaking to you at the Allen Brain
Institute in Seattle Washington where
you were wooed away from Caltech
amazingly enough that's right so before
we dive into your book just again to
introduce everybody just remind you why
you're here your new book so you haven't
even seen your book no yeah the feeling
of life itself why consciousness is
widespread but can't be computed okay
well yeah some people are gonna dispute
that but that's it before we get into
that though just kind of catch us up you
know you're famous for having worked
with Francis Crick when you were at
Caltech and you were had kind of the
traditional academic career just
grinding
doing your thing and then all of a
sudden you're now in Seattle running the
Allen Brain Institute what what is it
you're doing there and why did you do
that transition so we have three no 30
scientists focus on a few very large
projects in the brain sciences so for
instance we have a big nature paper
coming out next week where we look at
human brain material so either from
their brain or from neurosurgical
excised brain tissue and 20 minutes
later after the neurosurgeon takes it
out of the brain of a patient it sits in
our in our lab and then we can do what's
called single-cell transcriptomics so we
can read out all the genes that are
expressed in the different new ones to
get a view of how many types of
different brain cells they are in a in a
human compared to the different types of
brain cells in a mouse now many are
there in humans versus a mouse's well in
any one cortical area turns out it's
roughly the same roughly 100 and that's
the same number in human and mouse and
it's sort of similar the number of genes
when people first in the late 80s
identified 20,000 genes in the mouse
genome they said Wow humans are clearly
vastly more complex so they're going to
have hundred thousand or two nuts off no
they're roughly the same number of genes
we have roughly the same number of types
of different neurons probably across
entire brain on the order of a thousand
two thousand five thousand although
there are many many differences in those
difference matter so particularly if you
here for example if you are into making
drugs to help people with schizophrenia
or autism and you for example you're
after serotonin receptors and you make a
drug based on some animal that um in a
particular Mouse experiment well the
same the same serotonin receptor may be
distributed looks.i looks like it's it's
on different types of cells so therefore
what you found
you're fine in the mouse doesn't really
generalize to what you find in in human
so while the principles are similar the
details really differ greatly which
explains why some so much drug research
there was you know started in the mouse
you can cure mice but you can cure human
with that
and is that because just the
combinatorial complexity of you know
when you just start grinding along on
the the numbers of combinations and they
just don't extrapolate from one species
to the other yeah you got to remember if
you trace us back and down the
evolutionary tree the last common
answers to lived you know at the time of
the eye of the dinosaurs 65 million
years ago and so since then we we've
diverged your brains are build along
similar principle but all the details
have changed over the last 65 million
years
so you really gotta work with human
brain tissue which of course it's much
more challenging what year did Francis
died in 2004 2004 so it's 15 years what
what have we discovered since then that
he would be surprised about or pleased
to see solved or or still mystified in
the or whatever well so first of all I
was recently rereading there's a very
one of his better known articles was
written in 1979 well in 1979 so that's
basically you know that's that's 40
years ago when he just made the
transition from molecular biology to
neurobiology and when he also made the
transition from Cambridge England to La
Jolla here in California and he wrote a
very forward-looking article about about
brain sciences and some of the things it
should be invented and so their focus on
ba-leep he predicted well wouldn't it be
great if we have tools that light up
neurons with you know with flashes of
light when they when they have when they
discharge electrical activity wouldn't
be cool if we can turn you on
selectively on and off hmm these are all
tools that people developed over the Oh
over the last decade
so those things he would have been
comfortable with what he probably would
continue to be surprised at it's a vast
complexity of the brain you know even
you know when were when he and I worked
together 15 or 20 years ago we thought
there were going to be simpler molecular
codes that Express which cells are you
know sort of living in which bits which
specific part of the brain and all of
that turned out to be much much more
complicated than we were
we had imagined and some of the the
possibility to manipulate the human
brain again he might have been surprised
on the other end he was very fast
thinking so I'm not sure whether they
really would have been surprised by many
of the current developments I was trying
to find that famous quote for his book
the astonishing hypothesis what is it
you your joys and your sorrows your
memories and your ambitions your sense
of personal identity and free will and
let me see what's the rest of that quote
I mean it's still kind of true yeah are
in fact are in fact no more than the
behavior of a vast assembly of nerve
cells and their associated molecules of
course that's so broad it's kind of true
by definition but but why was that
astonishing at the at the time it wasn't
I mean it was a book titled that he
later regretted it was suggested to him
by his publisher never that would be
catchy no this is what most brain
scientists believed at the time and
believed to do
Tooley that ultimately who you are is a
part of your neurons also and this is
important it's not the same as us your
nuance right so my experience my love
that I have for my wife or for my
children it's not the same as the
neurons that that are involved in that
action those are really two different
things
one is necessary for the other right
it's sort of the physical substrate of
the other it's not my heart as ancient
believe it's not my liver that give rise
to my feelings it is the brain but but
the brain is different from the feelings
that that the brain gives rise to yeah
so there you're identifying the hard
problem of consciousness what it what it
feels like to be something or to
experience something yeah I mean yes
you're right so the hard poem is trying
to understand how one relates to the
other in a scientific empirical and
useful manner and of course some
philosophers claim this can never be
done me I don't know you know
philosophers have claimed many things
thought they hated said can't be done so
one has to be a little bit skeptical it
is indeed challenging it is difficult
there's no question about it yes so well
but the question is is it a conceptual
problem that is a problem with our
concepts or is it a scientific problem
that is is there any experiment you can
run and say there that explains exactly
why I experienced something well so it's
a we need an entire theory there's no
single experiment that will ever
convince anybody but it's the same in
physics if you look at quantum mechanics
you know as you well know Michael
quantum mechanics make some very weird
predictions right and so cook but
collectively we believe scientists
believe quantum mechanics is the best
description we have of the universe at
the micro scale and so ultimately we
need a theory of consciousness that
explains your consciousness and how it
arises in your brain and what happens
when you might get a stroke and what
happens in babies what happens in
animals what happens when you go to
sleep what happens when you have you
know various mental diseases and then we
have to see what are some of the
implications of such a theory for
instance for computers or for other
systems that we might not currently
think of as as being conscious well so
the title of your book the feeling of
life itself that is your definition of
consciousness ultimately yeah it's a
quite common one ultimately
consciousness is any experience any
feeling you have yeah you say
consciousness is experience yes yes as
in equals yes that's what yes
it's any experience that you have the
this subjective aspect it feels like
something you know to be angry to be
upset to know that you're gonna die one
day to be happy to be in love you know
to have a toothache to look at you to
hear me those are all different
experiences that's what consciousness is
yeah so but let's say you and I are both
looking at a red dot or whatever and in
back in our visual cortex at the same
spot is lighting up in an fMRI we would
say that's the neural correlates of that
conscious experience of seeing something
red but that's but where's the red our
mutual friend Deepak Chopra would say
where's the red well in this case the
experience is a consequence of the or
it's not a consequence no is it's really
the
you have a physical substrate let's see
some neurons being you know
interconnected in a particular way and
they are associated with this feeling
it's not that that first set is a
physical action and then there is a
feeling because that sort of dualism and
in scientists you know sort of tend to
reject that no you have the physical
constituency you have your brain or part
of it and then that sort of is
coextensive with a particular experience
whatever the expense will be seeing
rather being angry right it seems to me
this is this gets us to an answer to the
question of you know the problem of
other minds or how do I know you're
you're you're not a zombie and I'm the
only human that's actually sentient
because your brain is wired the same as
mine or very similar that the Copernican
principle says I'm not special so the
chances that you know you're completely
different on an experiential level than
I am even though we have the same wire
and is very low therefore the inference
to the best explanation is we're all
sentient perfect that's exactly I would
like I couldn't have better I could have
put it better myself now I don't really
know that but it's an inference as you
said it's an influence of the best
explanation yes right so well so that
gets to yeah well anyway just sort of
we're getting slightly ahead of
ourselves but you you know you you right
here consciousness has lived reality it
is the feeling of life itself is the
only bit of eternity to which I am
entitled without experience I would be a
zombie ain't nothing to myself so
there's there is all the neural activity
then there's this other layer of I don't
know what you want to call it I've sort
of a metaphysical layer or no it's not
yeah yeah that's my reality remember the
only thing I know off I said I have
feelings even anything else right but by
this definition that I would assume my
dog you have a dog I have a chocolate
lab I assume he's he experiences things
he there he has experiences similar to
mine therefore he is conscious yes
there's no question about it I don't
know by the way a single dog owner or
cat owner that would deny that that
their companion animals also have
feelings now they're not as complex as
yours or mine
my
my dog doesn't know he's gonna die one
day my dogs don't have that capacity I'm
not sure how much my dog you know thinks
about himself you know I like you think
about myself and I project myself in the
future I think about the past my dog
lives you know it's much more like a bit
like a Buddhist he lives in Bahia now
yeah he's very mindful in that in that
way most of us are not but yes he has
conscious experience no question about
it
your dog is enlightened in some sense
yes he's more enlightened because I'm
always obsessed about the future all
about the past most people are right
right because me think what would happen
then you replay the last dialogue the
last fight you had with your girlfriend
or whatever my dog doesn't do that my
dog is much more in the present yeah
yeah but so by this definition then it's
really just a scalable spectrum of like
instead of the lights coming on and off
like a switch of consciousness it's more
like a rheostat that you know you just
kind of turn it up it's very dim or it's
a little brighter and brighter and
brighter based on what the number of not
just a number of neurons but how they're
wired and in the complexity of the
neural networks and so on again you
you're putting it very well now that's
probably to pose at the level of
individual over your lifetime as well as
the cost species in other words when you
think back when were your first
conscious when when did you actually
first have an experience was it you know
when your your mom and your dad got
together and they you know the sperm
fertilized the egg was it at the stage
of blastocyte when you were 16 cells was
it at the end of your first term when
you had a brain you know after ten weeks
you have already a brain right and then
that goes is it when you when you exit
from your mom's womb into the world when
you finally have to breathe oxygen and
you scream and there's light and sound
and all of that or the or does it occur
June you know in the first two three
years of life when you get when you
would when you start speaking and even
as a teenager there's certain things
that you still have no experiences of
like like like the experience of being
in love or sex or wine of drugs all of
those right so you expand your conscious
experiences and then of course at the
end of life you know maybe there's
dementia
maybe you know you'll have a stroke or
something you know so so it waxes and
Wayne as it does during the day right
when you go to sleep your consciousness
is off and the same thing as you said
will change across different species
somehow scaling with the complexity of
their brain do you distinguish between
consciousness and sentience no I don't
awareness consciousness subjectivity
those are just different names but it's
all the basic same phenomena it feels
like something right you experience
pleasures pains suffering whatever yes
yeah that's why I always like Jeremy
Bentham's famous quote about it sort of
the grounding of animal rights not can
they thinking can they talk but can they
suffer yes yes ultimately I think that's
that's that's a key inside the suffering
the ability to suffer or not I mean
we're way ahead on this is you at the
end of your book on animal rights but
that's kind of where it begins and if
you really believe that then I don't
know how in the animal sentient beings
we kill every year it's like a trillion
a year if you count every chicken and
fish and so on I mean this is like worse
than the Holocaust every year so I
thought recently a quote in a restaurant
Germany and they said for for animals
its Treblinka every day
yeah and so I mean one reason I'm the
main reason I'm a vegetarian since many
many years because I don't want to do
that anymore you know certainly advanced
so I had this I had this epiphany the
night my beloved German Shepherd I was
fifteen years ago the black German
Shepherd know that she died in my arms I
was distraught and was crying and then I
thought well at the same time I loved
the the flesh of pigs and lambs and
their brain is roughly the same
complexity is that of my dog right so
they so I that night I promised my I
promised my nosey in her honor I would
never eat the flesh of another conscious
creature again and you did it and I
haven't what was her name nosy nosy nosy
she was intensely curious knows my black
gem shall I see nosy yes okay got it
black German Shepherd yeah German
Shepherds are they're really great dog
I've had two of those yeah well I mean
this is one of those things you think
like I wrote that book the moral arc and
people then ask well you know what's the
next stage well it's got to be animal
rights you know and it's one of these
things like if we were chronically
frozen and came back five hundred years
from now how would people then look back
at 20th century 21st century what what
we think about now you know they would
probably accuse us of being you know
like the equivalent of slave owners or
genocide 'el you know maniacs I think
there was an excellent point I mean we
today of course we believe we're morally
superior to every other previous culture
because you know we we have less races
and we have less misogyny but you know
but you're right they're horrible other
things that people simply don't think
about it when you talk to them about
about suffering some people would say
yeah you probably arrived but it tastes
too good
most people don't even think about it at
all
yeah just like presumably it it you know
when the Greeks were around nobody
really thought much about slaves I mean
I was total and Plato Socrates for sure
they didn't write really about it they
didn't even consider it a real issue
right not even noticeable
no yeah Dawkins wrote an essay
republished in his book the soul of
science I think about wanting to be a
vegetarian and he kind of went through
Peter singers famous arguments about the
expanding moral circle yeah well that
and he basically at the end he says I
know he's right and I know I shouldn't
do it but I go to a restaurant and I
can't help myself
you know it could be we need you know
everyone needs to change you know know
you need more than the arguments and you
need some kind of cultural momentum yes
and I mean that's why I took in my case
you know the in the death of my beloved
pet because you know I the taste of meat
is deep ingrained in our culture yeah so
it's just like with many of the other
isms we need to change our entire
culture why bring up children with all
this flesh all right here's your current
here's your current dog ah from your
from your perspective did you draw that
I know I had an artist oh yes because I
think movie
dog what's what's her name Ruby Ruby
yeah like the jewel yeah yeah right
anyway well I mean that's you know it's
one of those issues that I think
culturally will get there I think it's
going to take longer simply because
because we all have to eat and meat is
such a big factor you know it was easier
I think to give up slaves because not
that many people actually own slaves
everybody eats and everybody eats every
day and most people eat meat I think
it's just a harder moral revolution to
bring about I agree but there are some
promising development is impossible
impossible food there's your meat it's
getting more expensive and you know with
8 billion people it's not clear within
50 years from now we can still support
this mass ok culture given you know the
Associated environmental cost so maybe
things will will change I've been I've
been having the the impossible burger at
a local islands chain here in Santa
Barbara it's pretty good and I mean it's
a little expanding its 15 bucks or
something like that but the cost will
come down in time the council will come
down and apparently the impossible but
are they off it now at Burger King I
think it's the impossible West English
is I think they're calling the
impossible whopper yes and people can't
tell it apart so that's encouraging
yeah all right so this is the your
previous book was the about of romantic
what did you call yourself a romantic
consciousness a confession of a romantic
reduction projection a romantic
reductionist yeah yeah you've always
kind of flirted around with with not
being strictly reductionistic well and
yes
so that's entirely too very good and of
course in consciousness you have to take
a holistic perspective because
consciousness ultimately it's about a
whole you know w w o al e the whole here
and and because we you know my conscious
experience is holistic it's one it's not
many I don't experience many things at
any given point in time and so therefore
you have to ask what is a whole in in
your brain or anywhere else and and and
each whole concept
a conscious being a conscious thing a
conscious entity that has some
experiences yes yeah in the book you go
through these surgeries where they take
out different parts of the brain and
consciousness still is still retained
walk us through some of that research
and the search for where it's located
and why it's impossible to find it in
any one place well so so yeah so we do
know enough from new no clinical
neuroscience the last 150 years to know
there isn't any one place where sort of
it all comes together you know all my
conscious experience of me and not in
any one place they of course places in
the brain way if you have a stroke you
become unconscious but particularly in
the brainstem right so your brainstem as
like this to this pipe roughly two inch
a one inch thick to into the cause here
that connects the spinal cord with my
brain popper if you have a lesion there
you're typically in bad shape
right you may be in coma or or in a
persistent vegetative state but those
are just enabling factors just like you
need your heart to beat if your heart
doesn't beat within seven to ten seconds
you faint so that's one of the necessary
background condition same thing your
brainstem needs to all those neurons in
there need to be active in order to vote
for your for your really your cortex
it's really context the at the outermost
shell at least in as humans and in other
mammals that gives rise to anyone
conscious sensation and there we know
from people like Oliver Sacks you know
they're the neurologists yeah that
specific part of this cortical sheet
it's really like a pizza in assets like
a pizza
it's a fourteen inch diameter two to
three millimeter thick and you've got
two of them and they're highly convolve
dand you know you know put into your
into your skull and different parts of
that mediate different aspects of
feeling feeling of self feeling of
seeing motion seeing of color of hearing
and we know this from people who have
strokes or lesion they miss they miss
entire entire categories of experience
they don't seem color anymore they they
feel everybody else is has it sort of
has been at a place they the loss of
feeling or familiarity and so so
clinical natural experiments like that
we know their specific parts of the but
of context that are really essential for
different classes of conscious
experiences yeah I was liked about
Oliver's books is you know basically
each chapter is something that's gone
wrong in somebody's brain and then what
that looks like in terms of symptoms and
experiences and behaviors and what it
actually feels like he's really very
good at conveying you know the feet you
know how does the world how does how
does your experience of the world change
if you have you know if you have these
specific brain lesion or you're unable
to remember or you always live live in
the present and that teaches us a lot
about consciousness there's another
class of surgeries so medical sciences
in general and surgeries probably taught
us more about consciousness and most
other fields so a series of experiments
that I know you know well that were done
at Caltech by a remember Joe bogan the
new search and and Michael Gazzaniga and
Laura Sperry you know who got a Nobel
Prize forth with these split brain
experiments yeah and so what happens in
a split brain experiment of course you
have a person who's epileptic seizure
the seizure might start in one cortical
hemisphere so seizure is just a hyper
you know hyper excitable above and
electrical activity that can if it
spreads can engulf the entire brain and
then you get these core model' you know
these attacks so to prevent it from
spreading as spreading a radical
therapies to cut the why the why is
there tuna if you look down at the brain
right it's like a walnut they're two
halves and the two halves are connected
by 200 million fibers called the corpus
callosum and if you cut that that yes
beautiful exactly and if you cut that
you can you can prevent the seizures
from and from spreading but then it
turns out now you have two minds in at
least some of these patients you have
two minds inside one scow you have the
left brain that gives rise to a mind and
that's the one that speaks but there was
a great discovery that the the the
speaking parts is really specialized in
most of us it's the left hemisphere
Bacchus they are in Veronica's area but
you can shut that off focus on by
initializing it by injecting sodium
amytal
and then there's the other mind in the
right hemisphere and they don't know
about each other it's like being on the
dark side of the moon there's someone in
my hair but it's not me you know like
the Pink Floyd it's on quite literally
because each one is its own experience
each one believes itself to be the only
thing inside their body but then of
course the patient you can ask the
patient and sometimes the patient
complains the patient she or he will say
oh my other hands always does things
that I don't want it to do right yeah
because it's the other consciousness
that have also a will of its own and
then they have to duke it out yeah it's
the problem of identity and self is
there a single self if you can so easily
divide a brain into two my so easily I
mean it is massive you know it's it's a
pretty rare surgery it's not it's not
done that even yeah but if you
physically cut the brain into two yes
then there will be at least this way not
this way but if you cut it this way
there will be two now you can do the
opposite also so this is what I talked
about so I can take your brain in my
brain and I can do sort of the very
opposite of split brain so I can start
putting in wires between let's see my
visual cortex and your visual cortex
okay so let's see I have some future you
know neural link Elon Musk like
technology that allows my visual cortex
to talk to your visual cortex so at
first what what the theory that I
discussed predicts at first I can see I
see normally like I see now but I also
see a little bit through your eyes so
what you see is like a ghostly image
like you know augmented reality
superimposed onto what I see but I'm
still me and you're still Michael now
with the theory predicts it's integrated
information theory predicts that as I
increase the bandwidth of this
connection as I add more and more fibers
this to this artificial brain bridge
between your brain and my brain at some
point and it's very precisely defined
when at some point abruptly I will die I
will disappear Christophe will be no
more Michael Shermer
will disappear instead there will be
this new thing this uber mind this new
conscious mind that has foot
in that houses that lives in to brain in
your brain and in my brain it has four
cortical hemisphere it's Sisu for eyes
and hears through four years and it
talks to two mouths but a different
world it'd be a completely different
experience well it still has some of you
it still has access to your memories
this mind still has access to my
memories of course it will have aspects
of your personality in my personality
there could be big Freud's going on but
it will be a single mind just like the
bog the e there will be a single mind
you know I'll call it Michael Christophe
you know some some amalgamation of your
mind and in my mind there's always only
a single consciousness and then as I
progressively reduce that there's
bandwidth these wires between my and
your brain at some point abruptly you
will find yourself back in your brain
and I will find myself back in in my
brain the sensor I showed this picture
of your dog Ruby through your eyes you
know sort of looking down you can see
your legs and there's Ruby for those who
are just listening to this podcast if
you had a brain link between your visual
cortex and your dog's visual cortex
if you cranked up the electricity enough
would she suddenly see that almost like
looking in the mirror like there I am it
would well if it's a single mine it
would be a sort of a weird canine human
mind we would be fused yes it's it's
it's a very weird that is really spooky
I mean it's it's easier to think about
it yeah you know so for example when
you're making love you must have
realizes you know so you're making loves
you you're sort of your bodies are
interpenetrated but you realize that she
is assuming you're making love to a
woman that she is still her own mind and
you're still your mind and you can look
at each other but you can never bridge
that gap right mind the captors always
care now with brain bridging this the
the theory says if I directly connect my
pride mum my brain was harebrained and
at some point there will only be a
single mind we will truly be merged like
lavas there will only be one mind like
Kristen is older you know
in in in Varanasi eponymous opera there
will be one mind there will be no more
and there will only be twisting is olden
you know that I think it was a New
Yorker cartoon of two behaviorists after
making love the one says you know you
had a really great time how was it for
me
[Laughter]
know this now interesting this might
happen already on this planet there are
twins I'm thinking right now of
identical to Siamese twins in Canada mmm
yeah in north of us here in British
Columbia and they were born with what's
called a brain bridge and salami brain
bridge so due to some birth defect their
brains never really truly separated into
into two brains and there's some so the
New York Times you know Gordon long
article about it and there's some
evidence that one of the girls can look
there the other girl can look over the
end can partly see through the eyes of
her of her you know Siamese twin partly
because of this of this bridge so for
the one looking that's just such a weird
idea so they're really getting different
inputs and combining them into some kind
of field and I mean it I'm envisioning
some kind of a split field but but a
bird that has to you know eyes on either
side of its head
it I think of it like augmented reality
at that point right you know the
portable augmented reality for where
this car I see I see still the real
reality but then I have these virtual
images that are that are super that are
superimposed except here they are not
virtual they are again they're they're
real but at some point if there's only
one mind then this is your experience of
the world you explain you see the world
through four eyes I mean invincible yes
we we are of course only used to seeing
the world for two eyes but in principle
you can imagine how I see the world
soulful eyes a single conscious view is
singer mind maybe this would be so the
augmented reality may solve the problem
Thomas Nagel is what it's like to be a
bat yeah we can just actually put the
goggles on and they give the Aquila
sonar and you're now not a bad you
that couldn't you know your badge human
which is different from the pure path
that's true right so in that sense I
will never know really what a what
Justin bath is by itself because my
brain is different and so my brain
cannot be you know the brain of a bat
the most the most of that would happen
you'd just be a bat wondering what it's
like to be a human or something like
that I had a lot of experience with
virtual reality but I was at a
conference recently where the the
virtual reality goggles helmet thing was
a image from a hundred and ten story
building in LA or wherever it was
looking down on a plank sticking out of
the window and you walk out on the plank
so just standing there watching the guy
you know they were gonna if you can last
the whole two minutes or whatever it was
and you can walk actually walk all the
way out to the end you get some little
present whatever they were giving away
and and it to me it looked ridiculous of
course I could do this anybody could do
it because you know that the plank is
actually sitting on the floor one inch
above the carpeting but the moment I put
it on it's like I can't do it I am NOT
gonna be able to make it out there even
closing my eyes I would just kind of
open them a little bit in peak and you
know I'm looking 110 stories down it's
like I can't do it ourselves it's really
interesting it shows how that visual in
our case because we are visual creatures
visual input can override our prefrontal
cortex knowledge as you said you know
perfectly well there's no danger there
but the visual input sometimes it's even
more powerful when it's combined did
they have like sounds of wind no there
was no sound it was just just a visual
yeah the visual input by itself is so
powerful it can override your knowledge
it's like visual illusions idea I mean
you know this again there are these
powerful visual illusions you perfectly
well know you're being fooled but you
cannot not see the illusion my favorite
is Jerry Jerry Jerry Andrus is
impossible create illusion where yeah
yeah did the actual create built yes you
perfectly well know that it you know it
can't look like that but your brains
fools you because that knowledge isn't
sufficient to break the the individual
percept yeah
so what so the the musk mind-link or
whatever that's this thing is gonna do I
haven't really followed it that closely
uh but the moment they say you know
we're just gonna open up your brain and
stick this thing in there it's like wait
time out that's fairly risky surgery to
do that right just you know take open up
the skullcap and put something in there
and then put it back on that's not a
that's not a trivial thing to do correct
and so right now and for the foreseeable
next decade or two or three that risk
profile is only worth it if you have you
know if you're paralyzed or you know
Hemi player Parkinson's disease or no
toxin disease or you know if they're
significant if you're significantly
impaired all this augmentation right now
it's just simply too risky and no search
and in the at least in the West would
would do that because it's simply too
risky there's always a chance of
bleeding there's obviously a chance of
of infection etc and so you only do that
you know if you if they're strong
reasons to justify those risks yeah so I
mean if you had contact lenses that had
access to the internet or glasses or
something like that that seems fairly
easy to do a cochlear implant you know
that seems far far less invasive than
then what musk is proposing yes but you
know they people have done this now
brain machine interfaces in fact that's
also what knurling wants to do for
quadriplegic so these are people you
know wherever high up lesion in their
spinal cord who are you know can move
any of the limbs and so in that case
it's worth it you know in order for you
to control a wheelchair or to control
your you and your phone right so that's
that's such a great example of arthur c
clarke third law you know any
sufficiently advanced technology for
magic so all Geo's you see is this guy
is sitting there any and then things
start moving as he's thinking about him
well that looks like telekinesis unless
you know the the brain ship that's in
there how far is that come along since
it's still so you know if you look at
there are a few cases of these patients
online but then you you know it takes a
team of three four five six engineers
and three PhD students
a lot of support and you have to go in
the clinic and you know it takes you
sort of five minutes to take a single
sip from a straw so it's still very much
in its infancy but it's like any other
medical technology right early on all of
these things like contact lenses are
incredible primitive and then as
technology gets relentless better you
know these things will be easier to use
but as you pointed out any time you go
in vase if you go inside the body the
risk you know increases dramatically and
so that'll slow down any any technology
so adoption for most of us who are who
have not actually augmentation versus
just replacing a loss function it's
still a ways away yeah yeah now when I
read that I remembered my mom had
meningioma brain tumors and you know at
the moment they did brain surgery I
think she had to take like anti stroke
medications and and other medications
for the rest of her life yes just by
opening up the skull well she did she
had five craniometry these tumors kept
growing back and and then five radiation
treatments when they wouldn't operate on
the brain anymore and she felt Amelie
died of this but she was in a coma she
eventually she fell and hit her head
when she wasn't functioning too well and
was in a coma but so I was you know
reading your whole section here on
people in comas and or vegetative States
and so on and same kind of things so
many people experience I would hold her
hand and say squeeze my hand
you know and then she would do it pretty
much every time so what can we conclude
from I mean the lights are on a little
bit you know the dimmer has come up just
a little bit if she's responding in some
way or is that just more like a
knee-jerk reflex with a verbal command
ultimately it's difficult to know but
general the assumption is if it's you
know if you ask me if you hear me
squeeze my hand or you can also ask you
can ask him more objective knowledge you
know where you born in Kansas City or
not so people do those sorts of X you
know trying to communicate well you know
what the answer is and you see is it
just a reflex every time the the the
brain here's a command it just squeezes
or is it much more sophisticated more
challenging a case
what's called minimal conscious MCs
state or vegetative state where you
don't even get that where no matter what
you ask or you ask them to move their
eyes there's no response and there are a
few thousand of those patients and you
simply don't know whether there's
anybody home and then you need these
this technology that I described in this
book there's so called zap and zip or
you when you stimulate the brain it's a
little bit like you take a bell and you
hit it with a hammer and you're looking
at the reverberation and based on the
complexity of those who are vibration by
that you pick up using eg you can
ascertain whether the brain is still
conscious or whether it's truly in an
unconscious state like in a deep
anesthesia or in a vegetative state when
truly no one is home anymore you still
have the shell of the body like you
remember Terry Schiavo yeah she she
didn't even have a brain wasn't it just
mush or just mostly you know I don't
know she had a brain so she had an
anoxia for 25 minutes before she was
revived and put on a on a on a
ventilator and post-mortem they turned
out the brain at shrank by by a great
deal by more than half 50% but she did
have a brain and of course like many of
these patient in a vegetative state she
has occasionally these responses you
know where she would move she and the
eyes occasionally would move
occasionally she would grimace you know
it's very good see she laughing or
crying or what so she clearly had some
reflexes so so there's a difference
between brain dead when you have no
reflexes whatsoever and vegetative state
patience when you when they okay they
will open their eyes occasionally they
will they will move brain that patient
doesn't have any of that right so what
can you assume that in terms of
personhood or sentence said brain state
as fast we can tell if your brain is
dead you're dead
yeah your body may still be alive
although that's disputed but if your
brain is dead there's no one home
anymore and if you're honest um at the
modern definition of death it used to be
death a sensation of breathing sensation
of of pulse right but now we know that's
unique I can animate you right we people
invented in the 1950s ventilator so now
I can keep your body
live almost indefinitely so now we we
define deaths edom cut your palm mean
our death or a brain deaths if your
death if your brain is irreversible
broken then you're not home anymore
yeah although to your loved one you know
you might still look a lot you know
alive you have skin pala your your body
is warm your you know your your your
chest goes in and out but that's because
you're on a ventilator right well but
but I'm thinking of that that in between
state the coma state they squeeze my
hand and they do or whatever what is
well if they do then they are then they
are fully then they're there how much
are they there you know are they just
mainly there right are they just sort of
in asleep most of the time and
occasionally they wake up for an hour -
very difficult to to tell and with
technologies interesting you know again
50 years ago those people all would have
died very quickly but it was more than
you know 911 emergency it asks you
helicopters modern trauma surgery we can
pull some of them back and most of them
you know we you can we can return to
normal life but then there's this subset
of patients who's so gravely injured
they I'm not there but they're not fully
alive they are sort of you know hovering
in this unfortunate State and of course
with modern technology you can keep
their body alive for a decade was it the
Terri Schiavo case where the the husband
wanted to pull the plug and the parents
didn't or is it right yeah it was
litigated all the way up to the Supreme
Court a member of Congress met on the
weekend and the Supreme Court major
George Bush got involved yeah W Bush but
yeah so but that's not exception as I
said there are thousands of cases like
that mainly interesting homes hospices
etc and it's a great time it's it's a
great tragedy for everyone
yeah yeah right and then general
anesthesia
where does your consciousness or your
sentience go well it seemed pleased with
it goes when in deep sleep he's gone
it's benign it's simply it's not there
anymore because your you know your brain
is now in a different state you're
simply not not conscious that's what
defines states of unconsciousness yeah
yeah and then when you come the magic
you know you wake up you know I can I
can ask you Michael Michael and then you
come food and suddenly you it kind of
the lights come back on the lights come
back on again yeah the one enough at all
yes yeah
all right so walk us through this this
latest theory of you know neural
correlates of consciousness and the
information processing and all that well
I mean it's not it so they are really
two sort of popular scientific theories
scientific theories of consciousness
around one is the the global neuronal
works P theorem that essentially says
sort of it's a funkiest account that
essentially says consciousness is a
performance of certain function
involving short-term memory involving
planning involving self-monitoring and
and those things are implemented in
particular parts of the brain and also
once you replicate those functions on a
machine you know including monitoring
self having planning having ability to
speak etc then you will get a conscious
a conscious machine the other popular
theory is called integrated information
theory is by this psychiatrist and your
scientist Giulio Tononi and I'm a big
fan I've worked with them for many years
that says no consciousness is more
fundamental consciousness it's different
from its material underpinning it's a
distinct difference thing in fact it's
the only thing that I have directly
acquaintance with and and really has to
do altom Utley was with was a complexity
of any physical system ultimately it has
to do with with with the ability of any
physical system to to causally influence
itself ultimately it's about intrinsic
causal powers it's it's something else
total said 2003 not years ago you exist
you're conscious to them to the extent
that you have that your brain the thing
that is conscious has causal power upon
itself that means it can be influenced
by its previous state and it can
influence it can determine its future
state or self-referential
in some events a causal power ultimately
how do I know anything exists it really
goes back to
two fundamental ontological
consideration how do I know anything
exists I only know things exist by the
influence they have on me so gravity I
know it exists because there's tides
there's a famous Apple you know of Isaac
Newton that's how I that's how we know
ultimately gravity exists now this
theory applies causation to itself you
exist to the X you exist as a thing as a
conscious thing to the extent that you
that you have causal power upon your own
system and the more causal power you
have the more complex the system is the
more you exist the more you're conscious
and and and there are certain
consequences that you can test in
different dreams yeah and then it uses
something like that in his book freedom
evolves where he argues for something
like free will or volition as a function
of the complexity of the organism to do
what you're describing so the more of
that you have the freer you are or you
didn't say that he said the the more
degrees of freedom you have to make
choices within your environment to move
around and affect things and in the case
of humans we can self reflect on that
and know that these are the things that
cause me to do certain things so I'm
gonna change my behavior to redirect
that causal vector to do something else
that I know it will have that effect and
so on and so on in a self referential
way it's correct but of course Dan
Dennett
also fundamentally believes that there
isn't anything like consciousness itself
that's really a big illusion in in his
eyes we're really confused about it
ultimately consciousness is just a set
of behavioral dispositions ultimately
consciousness is a function I carry out
a whole set of functions I carry out and
once again once you implement those
function in a different system like a
computer that system will be conscious
so in that sense I this runs radical
contrary to his notion or the general
notion that's that such a myth in in
anglo-american University departments
and in big tech that ultimately machines
will be conscious because hey once he
can do everything we can do then of
course they're gonna be conscious and I
think this couldn't be more wrong well
then Howard yes
how would they how would you ever know
the machine was conscious well okay so
so okay so let's take this apart it is
true if you if you think about
intelligence intelligence ultimately
it's about behavior it's about function
and there's no question at least in
principle machines can do anything we
can doing including being creative and
speaking and talking and all those other
things where selves we are gonna be able
to write novels pretty soon at some
point yeah you can go to open may I and
you can use that GPT algorithm and it
generates pretty cool you know text pose
but that's there but but those are all
about functions yeah so there so
intelligence ultimately it's about
behaviors about function consciousness
is not about function it's not a state
it doesn't have to it doesn't relate to
function it's it's ultimately being it's
ultimately a state of being and yes in
evolved creatures function and
intelligence and continents usually
evolve together but you can certainly
artificially separate them and so you
can build a machine like deep mind or
you know Alexa you know 20 point
oh and fifty years from now that's
incredible smart smarter than you and I
but it won't feel like anything to be
this machine which is very different
from consciousness here which is
ultimately about being yeah my favorite
example of this is meeting David
Ferrucci the designer of Watson the
computer program that won jeopardy yes
so I asked him miss Watson know that he
won jeopardy I mean was he just totally
excited that he beat Ken Jennings and
and Brad Rutter and and and he's the
world champ no of course he doesn't even
know that he's playing jeopardy doesn't
even know what jeopardy is is it's just
an algorithm grinding through Wikipedia
pages to find the you know best
inference to the likeliest answer and so
forth yeah but most people Michael don't
have that into it most people say well I
mean dantana would suddenly say well not
what's maybe but if you make Watson you
know sophisticated enough it does all
these computation yeah of course it's
conscious because what else has
consciousness and carrying out a bunch
of functions so that's what what I mean
by but by my subtitle of my book
consciousness can't be computed it's not
just a simple computation so even if you
made a supercomputer simulation of
assumed being including
of its nuance that's just a computer
program that doesn't mean it's conscious
just like a weather simulation doesn't
make it wet right if you simulate a
rainstorm it's not wet inside the deer
hunt yeah yeah of course all the
different things but we are machines
I mean we're made of molecules atoms and
molecules that's a machine that's
correct so in principle you're entirely
correct so my brain as I say it's a
piece of furniture like any other
furniture okay it is - it is by far the
most complex piece of active matter in
the known universe
and so ultimately that if I want to get
a conscious if I want to build a
conscious machine I have to build it in
the image of man so you do what's called
neuromorphic engineering you build an
IBM has a project like that you're
actually trying to build neural hardware
neurons that have this massive overlap
in the input in the output that don't
talk to us - three or four transistors
but talk to 10,000 transistors yes so in
principle you can get a machine that has
human level consciousness but not
digital programmable machines right now
because their architecture at the level
of the metal of the actual wires at the
actual gates is vastly simpler than our
plane yeah but if we a so we just apply
a Moore's law out front on another
century or two and eventually we get
human level complexity it's still kill
no no so so yes you'll get human level
intelligence I'm not disputing that but
ultimately look conscience ultimately
it's a physical thing it has to do with
the complexity of the of the ultimate
Hardware not with a behavior so you have
to ask if you actually look at the CPU
you look at its wiring you have one
transistor gate that's typically hooked
up to three or four other gate or other
transistors whose very little overlap my
brain is radical different my brain has
one neuron that's connected with 50
thousand other neurons in the
neighboring you're may share 40,000 of
those inputs and outputs enabling one
may share 39,000 it's a it's a radical
different architecture this architecture
all evolved architecture really gives
rise to a high level of internal of
offer of intrinsic causal powers which
the theory is what consciousness is
which is very difficult it different
from simulating it in a digital program
on a vastly simpler machine no matter
how big this machine is so then again if
we're if we're a machine then how is it
that it happened with us but it can't
happen in a computer it cannot it could
happen in a computer if you build it in
the right way I said because the way we
build our machines is not to give rise
to consciousness and it is to do simple
things over and over and over and over
again right if you put in your tax
return or doing all these other things
that's what machines excel at and
they'll get better at it and ultimately
they may be smarter than us but that's
very different from actually having an
experience
look there's a great metaphor or great
analogy so I have a friend she's an
astrophysicist she writes down the
equation of general relativity to
simulate the black hole at the center of
the galaxy okay you know that there's a
there's a black hole at the center of
our galaxy it's roughly a million solar
masses but funny
she is not concerned that she's gonna be
sucked into the black hole when she
writes out the equation now why is that
it's a perfectly good it's a best
simulation invincible off of the power
of gravity yet where's the difference
why doesn't she get sucked into it
because it doesn't have the caller power
of gravity just because you simulate the
equations of general relativity does not
mean that you get the cause of power
that goes hand-in-hand with spending
space-time you know it's that mass does
same thing with constants just because
you simulate some of the behavior so she
was conscious does not mean you get the
same causal power that consciousness
Houston I got you okay so you're a Star
Trek fan data could never be a person in
in the sentient way that we are well
know I don't know what is hot ways in ex
machina right you know it's suggested
there's some sort of neuromorphic brain
you know it's never really explained
yeah yeah if it's if it's if it's
similar to the architecture of our brain
yes it could be conscious could even be
more conscious than I am okay so it has
to do with the purpose of the design
what are you doing able to do not the
purpose it has to do with the actual
and the actual you have to look inside
the box yeah
actually look at the hardware you know
there's stuff that actually does these
transformation and you have to ask how
complex is that using this specific
measure called Phi you can actually
compute for any particular piece of for
any physical system you can actually
compute how much fired hasn't principal
it's it's totally computable it's not
some very very mysterious stuff although
maybe this cause of power it's the only
thing that exists yeah so tell us what
fire is again so so much of thi your ph
are the Greek letter it's it's it's a
measure of officer it's a single number
between zero and and any positive number
if it's zero the system doesn't exist
for job is not conscious has no powerful
power pond itself the larger this number
is the theory said it's really a
quantity of consciousness if you want it
doesn't describe the qualia it doesn't
describe whether it's a smell or you
know the feeling of life itself or the
seeing red and so for that you need
different measures but fine self just
characterizes the the irreducibility of
the system how much the system exists
for itself ultimately it's sort of the
quantity of consciousness of that
particular system yeah so in my my last
book Kevin's on earth I have a chapter
devoted to the the people trying to
upload the mind the cingulate Aryans and
all that so I met this you know this
group that that are trying to not copy
the connectome in a in a scanning kind
of way they they want to actually they
sacrifice like a sheep brain froze it
and then and then sliced it up and then
scanned you know scanning electron
microscope of each of these slices with
the the idea at some point you'd have a
digital file that represents every sit
this is a group in Cambridge right yeah
yeah well yeah there's a couple groups
there there was one that was doing this
at a at a at a lab in Fontana California
21st century medicine that their main
job is is organ preservation organ
transplants and so on but then they also
have this little subdivision I'm not
sure they're still doing this but where
they would freeze freeze a brain
you know sacrifice the animals and then
infuse it with a president preservation
you know antifreeze so that water
freezing doesn't shatter the neurons and
then unfreeze it and slice it up and
then you can see that the synaptic
connections are still viable so this was
for them a proof of concept that you
could be if you could do it properly
with cryonics although they still have a
ways to go on this in principle the
memory self so they're defining the self
as your memories and I have a problem
with that because I think we're more
than our memories we're also our point
of view self through the eyes cell from
one moment to the next
and copying the connectome and then
turning it on somewhere else or putting
it in a digital file into the cloud
that's not going to be you it's not your
point of view looking through your eyes
self it's not your consciousness Michael
that's right it's not your consciousness
so leap yes leaving aside all
technological problems you'll be
actually doing this we have a project
here at the Allens dude funded by the
Aiyappa where for the first time we cut
up at electron microscopic level with
3.5 nanometer resolution a complete
cubic millimeter off a bra of a mouse
brain you know it's a it's a few
petabytes leaving aside all practical
methodological technological
consideration the theory very clearly
says if use run the simulation on a
digital cloud it's all fake
consciousness it won't feel like
anything it's digital rapture for nerds
and your your app into nothingness
yes so it's not you know it's nothing
it's nothing it's not even a thing it's
not even its self conscious correct it
wouldn't be a copy of you thinking I'm
the real Christoph Kok and that other
guy down there is just a copy correct
but you know I'm sure people will do it
because you know we're desperate to
cheat death in any which way and so you
know the finalists build this gigantic
pyramid so of course a modern version of
it you're gonna do the connectome yes
did you ever see that I usually a bigger
part there was a documentary film made
on Ray Kurzweil called the
is it the aterna no not the immortal
list it was the single yeah no not the
singularity is near this was on his
personal life and in any case it sort of
follows him around of course he has a
whole basement in his home devoted to
his father his father died at age 51 you
know and so he's keeping as much
information as he can that will be part
of the reconstructed essentially
resurrection really that's the right
word resurrection of his father but of
course the father isn't there it's just
you're interacting with a copy of that's
closer than a memory photo book say a
photo album people want to reach
immortality any which way and this is
the modern way of doing it's not that
different from the photo you know having
his slaves and and you know all of his
entire household killed and you know
putting his pyramid yeah
karakurt's wasn't in the basement it's a
little bit less glamorous than the
pyramids of the he of the flowers I
can't remember I think you were at that
conference the singularity summit was
meeting in New York City yes this was
right at the time of the Occupy Wall
Street I forget what year that was
and maybe 2009 or so in Ray Kurzweil he
gave his I have a dream speech you know
and I mean kind of reminded me of being
in church again like you know we are the
generation that are were the chosen ones
we're the were the ones that are gonna
make it rapture the rapture for nerds
yeah and then after he spoke somebody
else had a bunch of these little BOTS
that were supposed to be all coordinated
is like a hive mind on the stage and
they were gonna run around and do
something but they couldn't get it to
work because somebody had something on
in the room that was interfering with
the you know with the the system that
they were using and I thought well we're
not even close to having these little
robots working much some of the working
issues with heaven and I did there's
always going to be some issues with bad
words in heaven yeah I mean so I mean
this is just opens up just
the ideas I mean if you live forever I
mean what would that even mean in some
other the assumption everybody makes I
think is that your consciousness
continues even if your physical body
dies either in a soul or a copy of your
connectome in on some other platform
that continues we still picture
ourselves waking up in this other place
after the death of our body so it's it's
sort of a natural born dualism as Paul
bloom calls it you know we just have
this brain wired up to think that you
know there's something other than the
material stuff there is a mind as well
as a brain there's a soul as well as a
body and so on and it's almost
impossible to not imagine that in the
sense that if I say imagine being dead
you can't do it because to imagine
something you have to be alive so in a
way all this has to do with the fact
that we just can't imagine something
just epistemologically I don't know what
it means to not be alive well it's
interesting because people never think
about where they were before they were
born right but you know obsessed about
what happens after this but where were
they before they were born this is the
only boat that were they already in
heaven before and then they just got
downloaded onto this particular planet
that's right oh their life and then they
gonna go up again and of course it's
terrifying right - most of us you know
it is terrifying
you know the idea of seas of not
existing anymore is it you know I was
writing one of my chapters I dealt with
this terror management theory it's
called yeah based on the idea that
humans are the only species that know
we're gonna die and therefore we're
terrified by this and this motivates us
to be creative and build pyramids and
write music and and win Nobel prizes or
whatever
I think there's better explanations for
why people do that that have to do with
sexual selection theory and trying to
impress potential mates but that's a
different discussion but the but you
know again this idea that people are
terrorized by death I don't think so I
think most of the time we're not walking
around thinking oh my god I'm gonna die
maybe if you're 90 or something or you
have a a terminal illness but you know
most of the time I doubt that you think
about it well that's probably because
we're very good suppression techniques
right so it's an interesting question
when we
in evolution did we first have this
inside we were gonna die we were one day
not gonna exist anymore is it is that
neon assaulted me enough L know this
right is that the origin of religion why
did people when they first realized
hominoids that they were gonna die that
one is that one religion I think some
people are truly terrified I know and
not some of my acquaintances who you
know who are now constantly talking
about death obsessively really yeah most
of us I agree I'm not terrified by it if
I think deeply about it it's scary it's
no question it's scary right if you
really think about not being anymore
forever never ever it's certainly scary
but most of the time I don't think about
it yeah I don't believe in this terror
management theory yeah but people in
general particularly this culture where
we've removed death you know we don't
talk about death there's private dese's
takes place in the confine of a hospital
it's not part of our public life anymore
most people are suddenly uncomfortable
talking about it yeah think about it
yeah or be reminded of their own
mortality it's not polite
yeah right yeah no well so I've looked
into that in in my chapter on you know
what what who's the first to realize
this of course we don't know they these
things don't fossilize but there are
those grave sites Neanderthals and early
Homo sapiens with flowers and the in the
bodies are arranged and like a prenatal
condition where they're sort of you know
buried like almost like they're in the
womb again with some flowers and grave
Goods and so on the assumption is that
they're thinking well this guy's going
to continue on in some other state and
we're sending them off with some Goods
no grave Goods that kind of thing of
course we don't know I mean it's it's
like these you know werner herzog made
that beautiful film about cave art the
the dog what is it called they that cave
of these dolphin yeah now what was that
we looked that up I mean it's it's a
phenomenal film but you know you
basically we're looking at these images
that are 30 40 thousand years old and
thinking well if I did that what would I
be thinking you know that's just so
projection that's yeah but you know in
terms of biology we did I mean yes
there's still a evolution going on today
but our basic cognitive operate
both already fully developed 30,000
years ago Cave of Forgotten Dreams yes
yeah that's yeah they said yeah that's
right you can do that accent I can't do
that accent let's talk about altering
your states of mind this is becoming
more acceptable now doing it you know
like micro dosing hallucinogens you did
the you you write about doing the
floatation tank with your daughter in
Singapore I guess you did this yeah I
did this I know back in the 70s when it
was popular then I haven't done it
recently but yeah you strip down you're
in that it's almost like the salt and
Sultan of the Dead Sea and you float and
and and so I think I was in maybe an
hour and a half two hours and after at
some point I remembered not not really
hallucinating but I can almost see like
stuff was my brain was generating
stimulation as if it were coming from
the outside and what did you experience
well I have cause had the opposite
experience I had this what Buddhists
call a pure experience right so the
question is can you expect can you be
conscious without being conscious of
anything
all right so usually we're always
conscious of something I'd be conscious
of an adding headache or the the worry
that you know you have to deal with a
tax return or you know their sound a few
way or pain or whatever so the question
is can you be in the limit conscious or
not asleep but without being conscious
of anything and so my experience was in
the isolation tank yes you strip you
float in there so very quickly you lose
your bodily feeling where the
orientation because you're suspended is
totally dark of course you don't see
it's soundproof you don't hear then
early on you can still hear your you can
actually hear your heartbeat right and
at some point you adapt you adapt to
that in my case and you know I try to
quiet my mind you know of course all the
imagery of the residues of what I was
thinking in my you know that sort of
comes up you try to avoid thinking about
that and at some point at least I felt I
come to this perfect place where I'm
like suspended in nowhere and not
conscious of anything but I I but I'm
still somehow there it's it's a limit
state clearly because what would it mean
to be conscious without being conscious
of anything and it's very it's I found
it very very attacted and of course in
the Tibetan Buddhist tradition it's one
of the things that they feel they want
to attain the in fact aining this in a
permanent state is sort of one form of
off as close you can get to to being
enlightened yeah it takes them 30 years
to get there you did it in an afternoon
maybe that's a quick way to do it
it's obviously a quick and it takes this
artificial aid and and you know I did it
the second time and it didn't work the
second time the second time I was
constantly thinking about being in the
state I was too obsessed with it oh I
have to get into the state it's like
trying to fall asleep by making yourself
fall asleep by thinking about following
this exactly exactly exactly have you
ever have you ever done any
hallucinogens or anything like that yep
psilocybin and it's it's a wonderful
experience
right it's an absolutely wonderful
experience these all these colors and
and they're sort of more real than real
and and you know it's feeling some of
this ego loss so it's a little bit like
that and of course that's DMT right the
claim with DMT is and you know the
spirit molecule dimethyl ethylene that
you can also go into this black hole
state where you're conscious but you
lose consciousness of space of time
you totally lose consciousness of ego
you know this ego dissolution it's very
powerful but only short acting so that
may be another way to obtain this the
state of being conscious without being
conscious of anything and again the
theory says so the brain that's minimal
active will be conscious but without
being conscious of any one specific
content so it's not about function here
I was you know in a in a tank I was
fully conscious yet I was my brain
wasn't computing anything it wasn't
planning it wasn't speaking it wasn't
imagining it was just in a state of
being is that like the global work space
theory hurry no no it's very different
to a global work space so that's the
other competing theory was integrated
that competes was integrated information
theory in the man in the market space of
ideas say
that I'm conscious of a specific thing
like now I'm conscious of the this
question you just asked me so I have to
keep that active and I put that onto
this blackboard this is the metaphor
they use a black box architecture it's
going to be put in by them workspace and
then it's broadcast to the rest of the
brain so now it's all about answering
this question and then it's podcast am I
talking to my speaking module to my
planning module to my working memory
module and in the act of broadcasting
this is what gives rise to consciousness
sort of the act of broadcasting all this
information different kinds of my brain
that's what the theory says ultimately
it's it's about this function of
broadcasting which is very different
from from integrated information theory
although some of its newer prediction
may be similar but what I'm asking is is
is taking a trip like that does that
give us some information that supports
one theory of consciousness versus
another or is it yeah it speaks towards
more I integrated information theory
because global work space you have to
have a Content so per definition if
there isn't any content to broadcast you
wouldn't be conscious yeah would you do
it again why am i you would oh why don't
you do it every day or every week or
whatever yeah I know no it's a very good
question it's a very good question life
is busy and you know you have to if
you're too stressed it doesn't work mmm
it's an excellent question Michael why
do this every day I should actually well
so I mean my listeners is podcasters
gonna get sick of me telling the story
but I you know after being on Joe
Rogan's podcast with Graham Hancock this
is the alternative archaeology guy that
writes about places like gobekli tepe
which is something like a spiritual
center that's about eleven twelve
thousand years old much older than any
other monumental architecture so it's a
bit of an archeological anomaly I have
to admit but he as a separate part of
his his career he does a lot of
ayahuasca and you know DMT this thing
and he believes as do apparently most
people who do this do the ayahuasca a
trip and they've invited me to come try
this I've never done anything like this
that that they think it represents a
place that you actually go to that
you know opening the doors of perception
you know the arguments did you feel like
this is a different reality that exists
in some way or this is just my brain on
loose imagens well look I did
experientially I mean experientially
it's as real as anything else right but
I know because you know we study this in
in people we can study then animals it
has lawful relationship to the brain I
can partially induce it you know using
other physical methods so I know it's
something that the brain generates it
does feel real it's no question it
wasn't like oh this is all fake you know
like if you have you know if you take
follow-up psilocybin or LSD that it
doesn't feel oh this is fake no it's
real because it's the only real to your
app it's reality your brain generates
but then you learn it's very lawful it
as a lawful a relationship with doses
you know with particular parts of the
brain that are active the same parts of
the brain are gonna be active in you and
me etc so you know it has all these
lawful relationship and so we realize
it's kind of your brain your brain
generates in it's not that you're
physically traveling is just like I
don't believe when I dream I'm back you
know in honor on a climb that I'm
actually transported to your mouth no
I'm still lying in my bed my brain is
generating this dream mm-hmm but why
would the molecular locking key
mechanism even exist in the first place
why is it there oh because you know why
why is mine why do most of us appreciate
music
right it's a evolutionary span though
why do some people are why are some of
us very good at math did you know what
is really necessary for kommandantur
Homo sapiens to survive over and to out
do you know nyan Asano's it's an
evolutionary span all that happens to be
that happens to be useful for certain
things or maybe not even useful
pleasurable like alcohol you know you I
appreciate a Pinot Noir do I believe
that there's a specific evolutionary
reason for me to up to like Pinot Noir
no it's it's a side effect it's
something we discovered by experimenting
with lots of different drugs and we find
there's this one that gives that gives
rise to pleasurable social interaction
when you drink it none of the near-death
experience people argue that these
naturally occurring chemicals in the
brain are there for when you face death
when you are there at the at the edge of
helping you transition from here to
there wherever there is doesn't matter
if there's nothing there after death but
that it reduces anxiety about dying it
quells the uncertainty of it because
it's a real warm good experience that
people have this is one argument anyway
so that it's an adit it's an adaptation
estar Gyun yeah and I think that's - I
mean there well I shouldn't use
miraculous in this context but the
wonderful thing about near-death
experiences is that you can also have
them if you're not religiously inclined
and yes it it massively reduces the
anxiety that people have you know facing
death or near death and we don't really
understand the mechanisms you know why
that should be if we could somehow
understand them and then distill I'm
into some therapeutics and we can give
that to people you know when they get
into those states and when they are very
often agitated or very very afraid or
anxious yeah so it's a very interesting
phenomena that the dying brain
particularly the anoxic brain the brain
when it's cut off an oxygen some subset
a small subset of people you know 10
percent 12 percent can experience yeah
yeah the experience is real the question
is what does it represent something out
there in the world are inside the head I
think the experience yeah yeah you can't
argue with the experience experiences
early it's as real as any other
experience but again it seems to have a
lawful relationship to the underlying
brain matter yeah so what do you what is
your team working on in the future well
so with respect to consciousness you
know we're trying to a further push this
project where what are the neural
correlates of consciousness you know in
which part of the brain in both brains
of animals and in in brains of patients
and people and then we know this really
interesting collaboration called an
adversarial collaboration where we get
together with these people who have a
very different attitude to consciousness
the people
the of the global workspace where we
agree upon a common set of experiments
and where we agree ahead of time and get
this man is Capri submitted we're gonna
do this experiment we're gonna exactly
specify ahead of time what this
experiment is when it comes out in this
way it'll support your theory if it
comes out in that way it'll support our
theory it's called an adversarial
collaboration so it's really a new thing
in the sociology of science and we'll
see how that works out Congress should
do this well I mean it really in a way
we want to solve the homelessness
problem or the immigration problem or
whatever yes it would be great it would
be great if that were to happen same
thing with science we're all trying to
understand consciousness we're very
different takes to it so let's agree on
some experiment that could actually help
distinguish you know my theory from your
theory yeah I've I have a little excerpt
here from Steve Pinker's last book
enlightenment now about his opinion on
the hard problem of consciousness and
then I just get your reaction to this in
the end I still think that the hard
problem is a meaningful conceptual
problem but agree with tenet that it is
not a meaningful scientific problem no
one will ever get a grant to study
whether you are a zombie or whether the
same Captain Kirk walks on the deck of
the enterprise and the surface of Zack
Dorn and I agree with several other
philosophers and it may be futile to
hope for a solution at all precisely
because it is a conceptual problem or
more accurately a problem with our
concepts and he discusses a little bit
of Nagle's what it's like to be a bad
and and Colin begins running away with
that he says our best science tells us
that consciousness consists of a global
work space well you won't like this part
representing our current goals memories
and surround but even if that's wrong he
says the last dollop in the theory that
it subjectively feels like something to
be such a circuitry may have to be
stipulated as a fact about reality where
explanation stops in in other words we
may we've hit an epistemological wall
you know our friend Deepak Chopra he
that's what he says you know
consciousness is the ground of all being
it is the you know ontological primitive
there is no explanation for it because
it just is ok so that may be right
there's no law in the universe that says
everything will have a rational you know
reducible empirical testable explanation
just like quantum mechanics why does
quantum mechanics hold right we don't
know and people have thought about this
physicists why are we living in the
universe economy can you seem to be the
best explanation some people say it's
just a boat fact we just happen to live
in one end of discussion
yeah however we do have to be careful
you know our imagination is very
powerful what people said before can
never be solved you know then some neon
ideas later can be solved and of course
there is this now you may have seen
there several books that have now come
out about what's called pan psychism hmm
all right so pan site-- is his ancient
belief pan every website he sold that
everything is in sold that may be
shredding out they give the guy after
which the slitting equation of quantum
mechanics is named you know he thought
about this that maybe at the hood of
physics we have to include consciousness
so this matter and space and time and
energy but there may also be
consciousness this is what what ITR that
what the integrated information
ultimately says and so maybe we have to
include consciousness in our very
formulation of physicalism so maybe on a
Death Note and physicalism you know you
know the modern version of sort of
materialism has to be cast larger and
has to include subjectivity you know so
that I think that's a very promising
development so I'm very skeptical of
pessimists to tell me oh you shall never
know maybe yes maybe no I know for sure
if we don't I will not know it's my best
argument for cryonically being
chronically frozen and coming back five
hundred years from now and it's like Oh
consciousness we figured that out 200
years ago here's the explanation Oh
obviously
maybe maybe hopefully I just had that
Donald Hoffman on my podcast that I
think we released it last week yeah so
he's you know he has this interface
theory of perception you know that that
like your your laptop screen here with
the little trash can down in the corner
if you open up my macbook
Pro there's no trash can in there you
know these are just icons that represent
some process some algorithm that's
grinding along here and that's what he
says about you know the reality of you
know this cup is you know there's no cup
in my brain it's just a bunch of neurons
and this is just an icon that represents
something else
and so on but he's taken that pretty far
not quite the celibate ISM but but that
there is no possible way to know that
the true nature of reality yeah I mean
this is an old argument by Immanuel Kant
right if you ever read can't one of the
German idea list you know dusty talks
about dusting and Zee the thing itself
yeah and we have these categories of
space and time and causality we'll never
know what reality is really like it goes
back to our very beginning discussion
it's ultimately an inference process so
the most likely explanation is that
there is something physical called this
card you know how do I really know what
ultimately I don't know it's an
assumption I'm gonna go with that
assumption you know and it served as
well right it served us well making this
assumption allows us to manipulate the
universe to build you know nuclear
reactors and cars and and send rockets
into space so I think it's a reasonable
assumption would we really know what
it's ultimately like no we don't yeah
but the fact that we can send a
spacecraft to Mars and it actually gets
there and sends information back is a is
a pretty strong argument for there is a
reality yeah and we can know something
about it even if not everything about it
or perfectly represent it yes but yes so
you know it's an old idea yeah it is
cool I never know but I'm not really
sure what yeah I mean it's like this
problem I wrote an essay about why is
there something rather than nothing
Eve even trying to get our minds around
the idea of of nothing is not that
simple
I mean no thing it's a thing that's
there maybe we've hit rock bottom will
we ever be able to hand somewhere
there's anything either nothing I don't
know I I mean I love this quote from
Robert Kuhn he co-authored a book yeah
yeah yeah yeah you know you know
Lawrence cuz you've been
and always book about the mystery of
existence yes yes he wrote with John
Leslie yeah so he says you know and talk
about nothing that not just emptiness
not just blankness and not just
emptiness and blackness forever but not
even the existence of emptiness and not
even the meaning of blackness and no
forever I mean at some point you know
we've just hit rock bottom there's the
words just fall off the page and like I
have no idea what you're talking about
yes I think this is very likely one of
those cases you know it's I don't know
how much you've read about the mysterion
mysteries you know the the it could be
our brains we're just not big enough to
have the concepts to answer those kinds
of quitting enough to think of the
concept and the problem but not answer
it at least our conversion yes yeah or
you know Vic and Stein used the words we
use we don't have the right words to
have the concepts to even think properly
about it or not yeah things like that
yeah so I'm just talking about a little
bit easier things like called yes that's
right you have the easy problem the easy
problem of consciousness well the neural
correlates I guess sir this suppose it
easy but they're not that easy all right
so the feeling of life itself this was a
sequel to your you know romantic
reductionist what are you what what's
next on the on the Christoph agenda for
big big big questions I don't know I
mean you know I'm running this large
Institute with Serena plus scientists
we're very productive so on you know I
might take a break from from from
writing although you know right now I'm
several sonic American articles coming
out on brain death his brain Dias
irreversible there's some really
interesting you know science going on
there so stay tuned they're always
interesting things happening in the
world of neuroscience and unlike
cardiology let's say you are your brain
and you know most you know they're all
these fascinating ideas tied up with
your brain and your identity and where
do you go at night and where do you go
after after death and what can we do to
preserve the brain etc what's the future
of the Institute now that
Allen's gun so we are not secure you
know this was you know we we talked
about with Paul about this many times
they say estate his sister Jodie Allen
is in charge of the estate and and we
are now planning for 25 years
mmm we wickedly are moving on at 25
years trajectory there was there was
discussed at great length was with with
Paul Allen so we are here to stay the
earth and you're there for the duration
your yeah I mean you're not going back
to Caltech or being a professor or
anything like that I don't know I'm not
going back to Caltech well my exactly so
my presidency you know was for ten years
so that's that's gonna I'm gonna step
down from that in two years or something
like that and to return to a more active
role as scientists I fundamentally I'm a
scientist I love science and so I may go
back but remain here at the Institute
and just do signs and writing full-time
again because you're mostly doing
administrative work yeah I mean they're
three no people you have to make
decision what the fun but not too fun
you have no hundred employee I have six
employees and that's five too many I
don't know how you 300 yes it's
sometimes it's challenging and are you
still mountain climbing no I know here
because it's much more conducive so I
don't have a car i I just by Gabby being
a ho you know cool boring it's also much
more copia to the metaphor being a team
knows you know in a boat was eight and a
Coxon you're only as good as your
weakest link and you know no matter
whether people are big or small or of
you know my or you know have a big frame
or a small frame you know you have to
synchronize you have to be a team it's
not the star performers really the team
and it's set as a whole that counts and
so it is was our Institute here you're
like a single neuron with all these
other neurons that are somehow coming
together is a single brain yes so we a
team so what makes very different from
folks in university we try to only take
on one or two other things as a team and
to discuss so that has some unique
challenges as any other large you know
astronomy your elementary particle
physics project yeah yes
yeah and in do you guys work at all on
brain diseases like Alzheimer's and
senility and dementia
we will we're starting to think about
that so most of what we do is still
basic signs by trying to get the basic
layout on particular of the human brain
but assets become very successful we're
now moving into developing viral
technology for the human brain so in
other words once we know there's some
specific defect of a specific gene
that's missing in a particular type of
cell can we then devise technologies
like viral technologies to deliver that
missing gene to those right neurons in
order to cure people yeah so we're
starting to think about disease
applications yeah you guys got to solve
this problem before you and I hit the
wall because you know these people like
when I was writing my book you know it's
like Shermer don't you want to live to
be 500 I'm like look just get me to 90
without prostate cancer and a hundred
without Alzheimer's and dementia and now
these are hard problems and you know we
ask them through our mutual friend
Deepak I met you know Rudy tanzy from
Harvard he's you know like the head the
big Alzheimer's guy and it's like when
you really bore down on it you know
we're kind of clueless about the causes
and you know the plaques and tangles
yeah but what causes the plaques and
tangles no one knows is you know
genetics environment you know he has you
know general stuff you should eat well
and exercise and sleep yes yes yes I
know I'm doing that but what else and
you know show I do Sudoku puzzles you
know there's not much I think you'll
find I think you'll be fine just just be
very active yeah I mean but the brain is
by far the most complex system it's
vastly more complicated than any system
physicists have tackled with and it
might well be a while before you know we
fully understand these diseases and can
cure them yeah we just have to keep
trying oh it's Michael yeah I know it's
a pressing on your time now the book is
the feeling of life itself we will
release this on the day it comes out in
September whatever that date is and
congratulations on another good book
thank you much that was a great
conversation you are fantastic question
you always leave deep background I don't
know I'm kind of a dummy I just ask good
questions because I don't really know
I'm just curious you know along
okay I will see you next time I'm in
Seattle or next time you're right
yep all right